[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net SC radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software welcome to software engineering
radio I'm your host jaavan aspon and
today I will be discussing observability
for large language models with Philip
Carter Philip is a product manager and
open source software developer and he's
been working on developer tools and
experiences his entire career building
everything from compilers to high level
ID tooling now he's working out how to
give developers the best experience
possible with observability tooling
Philip is the author of observability
for large language models published by
Riley Philip welcome to software
engineering radio is there anything am
miss that you'd like to add no I think
that about covers it thanks for having
me thank you for joining us today let's
start with some ter ology and context to
introduce the subject so first of all
can you give us a quick refresher on
observability in general not
specifically for larg language models
yeah absolutely so observability is well
unfortunately in the market it's kind of
a word that every company that sells
observability tools sort of has their
own definition for and it can be a
little bit confusing observability can
sort of mean anything that a given
company says that it means but there is
actually sort of a real definition and a
real set of problems that are being
solved for that I think it's better to
sort of root such a definition within so
the general principle is that when
you're debugging code and it's easy to
reproduce something on your own local
machine that's great you just have the
code there you run the application you
have your debugger maybe you have a
fancy debugger in your IDE or something
that helps you with that and gives you
more information but that's sort of it
but what if you can't do that or what if
the problem is because some
interconnectivity issue between other
components of your systems in your own
system or what if it is something that
you could pull down on your machine but
you can't necessarily debug it and
reproduce the problem that that you're
observing because there's maybe like 10
or 15 factors that are all going into a
particular behavior that an end user is
experiencing but that you can't seem to
actually reproduce yourself how do you
debug that like how do you actually make
progress when you have that thing
because you can't just have that poor
Behavior exist in production forever
perpetuity because your business is
probably just going to go away if if
that's the case people are going to move
on so that's what observability is
trying to solve it's about being able to
determine what is happening like what is
the ground truth of what is actually
going on when your users are using
things that are live without needing to
like change that system or like debug it
in sort of a traditional sense and so
the way that you accomplish that is by
gathering signals or Telemetry that
capture important information at various
stages of your application and you have
a tool that can then take that data and
analyze it and then you can say okay we
are observing sort of let's say a spike
in latency or something like that but
where is that coming from what are the
factors that that go into that what are
things that are happening on the output
that can give us a little bit better
signal as to why something is happening
and you're really sort of answering two
fundamental questions where is something
occurring and to the extent that you can
why is it occurring in that way and
depending on the observability tool that
you have and the the richness of the
data that you have you may be able to
get to a very fine grain detail to like
the this specific user ID in this
specific region in this specific
availability Zone where you've deployed
into the cloud or something like that is
what is the most correlated with the
spike and latency and that allows you to
sort of like very narrow down and
isolate something that's going on there
is a more academic definition of
observability that comes from control
theory which is that you can understand
the state of a system without having to
change that system I find that to be
less helpful though because most
developers I think care about problems
that they observe in the real world sort
of what what I mentioned and what they
can do about those problems and so
that's what I try to keep a definition
of observability rooted in it's about
asking questions about what's going on
and continually getting answers that
help you narrow down behavior that
you're seeing whether that's an error or
a spike in latency or maybe something is
actually fine but you're just curious
how things are actually performing and
what healthy performance even means for
your system finding a way to quantify
that that that's sort of what the heart
of observability is and what's important
is that it's not just something that you
do sort of on a reactive basis like you
get paged and you need to go do
something but you can also use it as one
of your foundations for building your
software because as we all know there
there's things like unit testing and
integration testing and things like that
that help when you're building software
and I think most software Engineers
would agree that you want to build
modern software with those things but
there's another component which is what
if I want to deploy these changes that
are going to impact a part of the system
but it may not necessarily be a part of
a feature or you know we're not ready to
release the feature yet but we want that
feature release to be stable and like
easy and not a surprise and all of that
from like a system Behavior standpoint
how do I build with production in mind
and and use that to influence things
before I like flip a feature flag that
allows something to be exposed to a user
again that's sort of where observability
can sort of fit in there and so I think
part of why this had such sort of a
long-winded definition if you will or
explanation is because it is a
relatively new phenomenon there have
been organizations such as Google and
Facebook and all of that who have been
practicing these sorts of stuff for
quite a while these practices and
building tools around them but now we're
we're seeing a broader software industry
adoption of this stuff because it's
needed to be able to go in the direction
that people want to actually go and so
because of that definitions are sort of
Shifting and problems are shifting
because not everybody has exact same
problems as your Googles or Facebooks or
or whatnot and so it's a exciting place
to be in okay that's fine then now let's
go to the next bit llms large language
model what is a large language model I
mean everybody nowadays talks about CH
GPT that seems to be all over the place
but I'm not sure that everybody
understands at least you know to a high
level yeah what the large language model
is can you tell us a bit so a large
language model can be thought of
in a couple different ways I'll say
there's a very easy way to think of them
and then there's a a more fundamental
way to think of them so the easy way to
think of them is from an end user
perspective where you already have
something that's largely good enough for
your task it is a black box that you
submit text to and then it has a lot of
information compressed inside of it that
allows it to analyze that text and then
perform an action that you give it like
a set of instructions such that it can
emit text in particular format that
contains certain information that you're
looking for and so there can be some
interesting things that you can do with
that different language models are
better for like emitting code versus
emitting poetry some like chat GPT are
super super large and they can do both
very very well but there are specialized
ones that can often be better for very
specific things and there are also ways
to feed in data that was not a part of
what this model was trained on to sort
of ground a result in in a particular
set of information that you want an
output to be in and it's basically just
this engine that allows you to do these
sorts of things and it's very general
purpose so if you need for example to
emit Json that you want to insert into
another part of your application
somewhere it's generally applicable
whether you are building a health care
app or a financial services app or if
you're in consumer technology or
something like that it's broadly
applicable with which is why it's so
interesting now there's also a bit more
of a fundamental definition of this
stuff so the idea is language models you
know they're not necessarily new they've
been around since at least 2017 arguably
earlier than that and they are based on
what is called the Transformer
architecture and a principle or a
practice I guess you could say in
machine learning called attention and so
the idea generally speaking is that
there were a lot of problems in
processing text and natural language
processing with previous machine
learning model architectures and the
problem is that if you give like a
sentence that contains several pieces of
information inside of that there may be
a part of this sentence that refers to
another part of the sentence like
backwards or forwards and like the whole
thing contains this like strong semantic
relevance that as humans we can we can
understand and and form those
connections very naturally but
computationally speaking it's an extreme
extremely complex problem and there have
been all these variations in trying to
figure out how to efficiently do it and
attention is this principle that allows
you to say well we're going to
effectively hold in memory all of the
permutations of like this semantic
meaning of a given sentence that we have
and we're going to be able to pluck from
that memory that we've developed at any
given moment as we generate so as we
generate an output we look at what the
input was we basically hold in memory
what all of those things were now that's
a gross oversimplification there is
piles and piles of engineering work to
do that as efficiently as possible and
Implement all these shortcuts and all of
that but if you could imagine if you
have a program that has no memory
limitations if you have let's say an
nsquared memory algorithm that allows
you to sort of hold everything in memory
as much as you want and refer to
anything at any point in time and refer
to all the connections to all the
different things then you can in theory
output something that is much more
useful than previous generations of
models and that's sort of the principle
that underlies large language models and
why they work so well referring to these
models now I'd like to definitions of
two more terms that we hear all the time
so the first one is fine-tuning I think
you hinted at it before when you were
explaining what to do with a model so
can you give us what does it mean to
fine-tune a model yes so it's important
to understand the phases that a language
model or a large language model goes
through in sort of its productionizing
if you will there is the initial
training sometimes it's broken up into
what's called pre-training and training
but it's basically you take your large
Corpus of text let's say a snapshot of
the internet and that is data that is
fed in to create a very large model that
that operates on language hence the name
language model or large language model
then there's a phase that is often it's
within the field of what's called
alignment which is basically you have a
goal like you want this thing to be able
to be good at certain things or say you
want it to minimize harm you don't want
it to tell you how to create bombs or
like you know that snapshot of the
internet might contain some things that
are frankly rather horrible and you
don't want that to be a part of the
outputs of the system and so this sort
of alignment thing is a form of tuning
it's not quite fine-tuning but it's a
sort of a way to tune it such that the
outputs are going to be aligned with
what your goals and principles are
behind this system that you're creating
now then you get into forms of
specialization which is where fine
tuning comes in and depending on the
model architecture it may be something
that like once you f tuned it in a
particular way you can't like really
fine-tune it in another way like like
it's sort of optimized for one
particular kind of thing so that's why
if you're curious looking at all the
different kinds of fine tuning that's
going on there's there's so many
different models that you could
potentially fine-tune but fine-tuning is
that act of specialization so it's been
trained it's been aligned to a general
particular goal but now you have a like
a very much more narrow set of problems
that you want it to focus on and what's
critical about fine-tuning is it allows
you to bring your own data so if you
have a model that is good at outputting
text in a Json format for example well
it may not necessarily know about the
specific domain that you want it to
actually output within like you care
about emitting Json but it needs to have
a particular structure and maybe this
field and this subfield need to like
have a particular Association and they
they have some sort of underlying
meaning behind them now if you have a
corpus of knowledge of textual knowledge
that explains that what you can do is
fine-tuning allows you to specialize
that model so it understands that Corpus
of knowledge and is almost in a way sort
of overfitted on it so that the output
is a a language model that is very very
good at the understanding the data that
you gave it and the tasks that you want
it to perform but it loses some of the
ability especially from a output
standpoint that that it may have started
from so you basically overfit it towards
a particular use case and so the reason
why this is interesting and potentially
a trade-off is you can in theory get
much better outputs than if you were to
not
fine-tune but that often comes at the
expense of if you didn't quite fine-tune
it right it can be overfit for a very
specific kind of thing and then a user
might expect like a slightly more
General answer and it may be incapable
of actually producing such an answer and
so anyways it's kind of longwinded but I
think it's important to understand that
fine tuning fits in in sort of this like
pipeline if you will of like different
stages of producing a model and the
output itself is a language model it's
really like the model is different
depending on each phase that you're in
and so that's largely what fine tuning
is and where it fits in and then the
final term I'd like to Define here we
hear a lot is prompt
engineering so what is it about I mean
sometimes looks like a kind of sorcery
he's if you have to ask be able to ask
the right questions to have the answers
you want but what is a good definition
for it so prompt engineering I like to
think of it by analogy and then with a
very specific definition so through
analogy when you want to get an answer
out of a database that uses SQL as its
input you construct a SQL statement uh
SQL expression and you run that on the
it knows how to interpret that
expression and optimize it and then pull
out the data that you need and maybe if
you have different data in a different
shape or you're using different
databases you might have slightly
different Expressions that you sort of
give this database engine depending on
which one you're using but that's how
you you interact with that system
language models are similar to the
database and the prompt which is just
English usually but you can also do it
in other languages is sort of like your
sequel statement that you're giving it
and so depending on the model you might
have a different prompt that you need
because it may interpret things a little
differently and also just like when
you're doing database work right it's
not just any SQL that you need to
generate especially if you have a fairly
complex task that you want it to do you
need to spend a lot of time really
crafting good SQL and like you may get
the right answer but maybe really
inefficient and and so there's a lot of
work involved there and a lot of people
who can specialize in that field it's
the exact same thing with language
models where you construct basically a
set of instructions and maybe you have
some data that you pass as well through
a task called retrieval augmented
generation or rag as it's often called
but it's all in service towards getting
this blackbox to emit what you want as
as effectively and efficiently as
possible and instead of using a language
like SQL to generate that stuff you use
English and where it's a little bit
different and I think where that analogy
kind of breaks apart is when you try to
get a person or let's say a toddler like
a three or foury old to go and do
something you need to be very clear in
your instructions you might need to
repeat yourself you may have thought you
were being clear but they did not
interpret it in a way that you thought
they were going to interpret it and so
on right that's sort of what prompt
engineering kind of is if you could also
Imagine This database that's really
smart at emitting certain things is sort
of like a little toddler as well it may
not be very good at following your
instructions so you need to get creative
in how you are instructing it to do
certain things that's sort of the field
of prompt engineering and the the act of
prompt engineering and it can involve a
lot of different things to the point
where calling it an engineering
discipline I think is actually quite
valid and I've come to prefer the term
AI engineering instead of prompt
engineering because it encompasses a lot
of things that happen Upstream before
you actually submit a prompt to a
language model to get an output but
that's the way I like to think of it
what is observability in the context of
large language models and why does it
matter so if you recall when I was
talking about observability you may have
have a lot of things going on in
production that are influencing the
behavior of your system in a way that
you can't like debug on your local
machine you can't reproduce it and so on
this is true for any modern Software
System with large language models it's
that exact same principle except the
pains are felt much more acutely because
now in practice with normal software yes
you may not be able to debug this thing
that's happening right now but you might
be able to debug some of it in the
traditional sense or maybe actually can
reproduce certain things you may not be
able to do it all the time but maybe you
can in large language models that that
sort of everything is in a sense
unreproducible
non- debuggable non-deterministic in its
outputs and on the input side your users
are doing things that are likely very
very different from how they would
interact with normal software right if
you consider a UI there's only so many
ways that you can click a button or or
select a drop down and a UI you can
actually account for all of that in your
test cases but if you give someone a
text box and you say input whatever you
like and we're going to do our best to
give you a reasonable answer from that
inputs you cannot possibly unit test for
all the things your users are going to
do and in fact it's a big disservice to
the system that you're building to try
to understand what your users are going
to do before you actually go live and
give them the dam thing and let them
bang around on it and see what actually
comes out and so as it turns out
this way that these models behave is
actually a perfect fit for observability
because if observability is about
understanding why a system is behaving
the way it is without needing to change
that system well if you can't change the
language model which you usually cannot
or if you can it's a very expensive and
timec consuming process how do you make
progress because your users expect it to
improve over time it's what you release
first is likely not going to be perfect
it may be better than than you thought
but it may be worse than you thought how
do you do that observability and
Gathering signals on what are all the
factors going into this input right what
are all the things that are that are
meaningful Upstream of my call to a
large language model that potentially
influence that call and then what are
all the things that happen Downstream
and what do I do with that output what
is that actual output and Gathering all
of those signals so not just user input
and large language model output but if
you made 10 decisions Upstream in terms
of gathering contextual information that
you want to feed into the large language
model what were those decision points
because if you made a wrong decision
that will influence the out like the
model might have actually done the best
job that it could but you fed it bad
information how do you know that you're
feeding it bad information you capture
the user input what kind of inputs are
people doing are there patterns in their
input are they expecting it to do
something even though they gave it vague
instructions basically is that something
you want to solve for or is that
something that you want to error out on
if you get the output and the output is
what I like to call mostly correct right
you expect it to follow a particular
structure but one piece of it is a
little bit wrong are there ways that you
can actually correct that and make it
seem as though the language model
actually did produce the correct output
even if it didn't quite give you the
right thing that you were expecting
these are interesting questions that you
need to explore and really the only way
that you can do that is by practicing
good observability and capturing data
about everything that happened Upstream
to your call to a language model and
things that happen on the output side of
it so you can see what influences that
output
and then that when you can isolate that
with an observability tool and you can
say okay when I have an input that looks
like this and I have these kinds of
decisions and then this output pretty
reliably is bad in this particular way
cool this is a very specific bug that I
can now go and try to fix and my act for
fixing that is frankly a whole other
topic but now I have something concrete
that I can address rather than just
throwing stuff at the wall and doing
guess work and hoping that I improve a
system so that that's why observability
intersects with systems that use
language models so well are there any
similarities of observability for larg
language models with observability for
let's say more well in quotes
conventional systems there certainly can
be so I'll use the database analogy
again so imagine your system makes a
call to a database and it gets back a
result and you transform that result in
some way and feed it back to the user
somehow well you may be making decisions
Upstream of that database call that
influence how you call the database and
the net result is like a bad result for
the user even though like your database
query was not wrong it was just the data
that you parameterized into it or
something like that or or the decision
that you made to like call it this way
instead of this way that's a thing
that's actually wrong and now you can go
and fix that and and it may it may have
manifested in a way that made it look
like the database was at fault but
something else was at fault another way
that this this can manifest is in
latency so language models like frankly
other things have a latency component
associated with them and people don't
like it when stuff is slow so you might
think oh well the language model we know
that that has high latency it's being
really slow opening eyes being really
slow and then you go and look at it and
it's actually not that slow you're like
huh well this took five seconds but only
2 seconds was a generation where the
heck are those other 3 seconds coming
from now swap out the language model for
any other component where there's
potential for high latency and you may
think that that component is responsible
but it's actually not it's like oh
Upstream we made five Network calls when
we thought we were only making one oops
well that's great we were able to fix
the problem it was actually us I've run
into this several times at honeycomb we
actually have one of our customers who
uses language models extensively in in
their applications they actually had
this exact workflow where their users
were reporting that things were slow and
they were complaining to open about it
and open AI was telling them we're like
we're actually serving you fast requests
I don't know what's going on but it's
your fault and so they instrumented with
open Telemetry and tracing of of their
systems and they found that they were
making tons of network calls before they
ever called The Machine learning model
and they're like well wait a minute what
the heck and so they fixed that and all
of a sudden their user experience was
way better now about the challenges that
observability for large language models
helps to address so I think you
mentioned before the fact that with
these models is you know unit testing
for example or any kind of say testing
as some strong limitations with what we
can do we you cannot test a text box
where you can put random questions tests
and the model response to those so you
cannot have a a good set of tests for
that so there there is that but what
other kind of challenges observability
helps to address two important ones come
to mind so the first is one of latency
so I kind of mentioned that before but
large language models have high latency
and there's a lot of work being done to
improve that right now but if you want
to use them today you're going to have
to introduce latency on the order of
seconds into your system and if your
users are used to getting everything on
the order of milliseconds well that
could potentially be a problem now I
would argue that if it's clear that
something is an AI the phrase with large
language models usually most people
associate with AI a lot of users now
sort of are expecting okay this might
take a little while to get an answer
but still if if they're sitting around
tapping their feet waiting for this
thing to finish that's not a good
experience for someone and the right
latency for your system is going to
depend on what their users are actually
trying to do and what they're expecting
and all of that but what that means is
kind of to that point about you can be
making a mistake unrelated to the
language model that gives the impression
of a higher latency that makes those
problems more severe because now that
you have created a step change in your
latency on the order of seconds and you
have other stuff layered on top of that
your users might be like wow this AI
feature sucks because it's really slow I
don't know if I like it very much
getting a handle on that is very
difficult now in addition to that the
way that a model is spoken to right the
The Prompt that you feed it and the
amount of output that it has to generate
to be able to get a complete answer
greatly influences the latency as well
so for example there is a prompting
technique called Chain of Thought
prompting now Chain of Thought prompting
you can go look it up but the idea is
that it forces the model to so-call like
think step by step for every output that
it produces and so that's great because
it can it can increase the accuracy of
outputs and make it more reliable but
that comes at the cost of a lot more
latency because it does a lot more
computational work to do that um
similarly like you know imagine you're
solving a math problem think step by
step instead of intuitively it's going
to take you longer to actually get a
final result
that's exactly how these things work and
so you may perhaps want to AB test
because you're trying to improve
reliability okay what if we do Chain of
Thought prompting now our latency went
up a whole lot what like how do you
systematically understand that impact
that's where observability comes in also
on the output side you need to be
creative in terms of how it generates
outputs right things like chat GPT and
stuff they will output a dump of text
but that's usually not appropriate for
any especially any kind of Enterprise
use case and so there's this question of
okay how do we influence our prompting
or perhaps our fine-tuning such that we
can get the most minimal output possible
because that's actually where the
majority of latency comes in from a
language model it's generation task
depending on how it generates and how
much it needs to generate can introduce
a large amount of latency into your
system so instead of a large language
model you have a large latency model and
nobody likes that so again how do you
make sense of that the only way to do
that is by gathering real real world
data these is what real people are
entering in these are the real decisions
that we made based off of their
interactions and this is the real output
that we got this is how long it took
that's a problem that needs solving and
observability is really the only way to
get that the second piece that this
solves it gets to the to the
observability driven development kind of
thing so observability driven
development is a practice that is fairly
nent but the idea is that if you break
down the barrier between development and
produ C and you say that okay well this
software that I'm writing is not the
code on my machine that I then push to
something else and then it goes live
somehow but really I am developing with
a live system in mind then that's likely
going to influence what I work on and
make sure that I'm focusing on the right
things and improving the right problems
that's something that large language
models really sort of force an issue on
because you have this live system that
you're probably pretty motivated to
improve and it's behaving in a way right
now that is perhaps not necessarily good
and so how do I make sure that when I'm
developing I know that I'm focusing on
things that are going to be impactful
for people that's where observability
comes in I get those signals I get sort
of what I mentioned that sort of way
that I can isolate a very specific
pattern of behavior and say okay that's
a bug that I can work on getting that
specificity and getting that Clarity
that this is what is actually occurring
out in the world is crucial for any kind
of development activity that you do
because otherwise you're just just going
to be improving things at the margins is
this related to I read your book so is
related to your book to the you know the
Early Access program example you give
where say with limited user testing
especially large language models you
cannot possibly get all the possible
user behaviors because of you know the
fact that is a large language model is
not a standard application so this seems
like this case of observability driven
development is you get a go out with
something but then you check what the
users do and somehow use that
information to refine your system and
make it better for the users am I
understanding that correctly that's
correct I think a lot of organizations
in fact are used to the idea of An Early
Access program like a closed beta or
something like that as a way to reduce
risk and so that could in theory be
helpful with large language models if
it's a large enough program with a
diverse enough amount of users but
getting that degree of population like
enough people with a diverse enough set
of like interests and things that
they're trying to accomplish is often so
difficult and time consuming that you
might as well have just gone live and
seeing what people are doing and just
acted on that right away and what that
what that means though is that you need
to commit to the fact that you are not
done just because you've released
something and I think a lot of Engineers
right now are used to the idea that
something goes live in production the
featur is launched maybe there's you
sprinkle a little bit of monitoring on
that but that might be another team's
concern anyways I can can just move on
to the next task that is absolutely not
what's going on here the real work
actually begins once you are live in
production because I would posit that I
didn't write this in the book but I
would posit that it's actually easy to
bring something to Market when you use
large language models because they are
so damn powerful for what they can do
right now that for you to create even
just a marginally better experience for
people you can do that in about a week
with a bad UI and then expand that out
to a month with an engineering team and
you probably have a decent enough UI
that that's be acceptable for your users
so you have about a month that you can
use to take something to market for I
would wager a large majority of the
features that people use large language
mods for actually I have a question
related to this now that just came to my
mind so basically seems that we need to
replace the attitude of okay we've done
the feature the feature is ready
somebody will test in QA QA is happy you
release it because for this there is no
real QA per se because we can't really
do a lot I mean we can try a bit we can
play with a Model A little bit and and
say okay it seems to be good but in
reality until there are lots of people
using it we have no no idea of how it
performs oh yeah absolutely and what you
will find is that people are going to
find use cases that work that you had no
idea we going to work we observe this a
lot with our own feature at honeycomb
with our query assistant feature that's
our natural language data querying there
are use cases that we did not possibly
think of that apparently quite a few
people are doing and it works just fine
and there's no way we would have figured
that out unless we went live if you come
across I don't know among your customers
customers that had the more kind of
let's say traditional mindset with
development QA approach and then going
to production going to this large
language model and being may be confused
by you know not having the QA accepted
part before going to production I don't
know is something that you experienced
I've definitely experienced that so
there's really two things that I found
so first of all for most like larger
Enterprise organizations there's usually
some degree of excitement at the higher
level like the executive staff level to
adopt this technology in a way that's
useful but then there's also sort of a
pincher motion there there's usually
some team at the bottom that wants to
explore and wants to experiment anyways
and so what usually happens is they have
that goal and on the executive side I
think most technology Executives have
understood the fact that this software
is fundamentally different from other
software and so teams may need to change
their practices and they don't really
know how but they're willing to say hey
we have this typical process that we
follow but we're not going to follow
that practice right now we need to
figure out what the right process
actually is for this software and so
we're going to let a team go and figure
that out that team that goes and figures
that out on the other end I found when I
went and did a bunch of user interviews
they find out very very quickly that
their tool set for making software more
reliable practically needs to get thrown
out the window now not entirely there's
certain things that certainly are better
for example with prompt engineering
Source control is very important it's
very important for software it's also
very important for prompt engineering
get Ops based workflows that kind of
stuff are actually very good for prompt
engineering workflows and especially
different kinds of tagging like you may
have had a prompt that was a month old
but like it actually performs better
than the thing that you've been working
on and how do you sort of systematically
keep track of that so people are finding
that out but they're finding out very
very quickly that they can't
meaningfully unit test they can't
meaningfully do integration tests they
can't rely on a QA thing they need to
have just a bunch of users come in and
just do whatever they feel like with it
and capture as much information as they
can and the way that they're capturing
that information may not be ideal some
are actually realizing that we talked
with one organization that was just
logging everything and then finding out
that sort of what I mentioned that
there's often these Upstream decisions
that you make prior to a call that
influence the output and they would have
to like manually correlate this stuff
and eventually they realized oh this is
actually a tracing use case so let's
figure out what's a good tracing
framework where we can capture the same
data and almost sort of stumbled their
way into a best practice that some teams
may know is appropriate but like so
there's this pains that people are
feeling and recognition that they have
to do something different that I think
is really important because I don't
think it's very often that software
comes along and forces engineers and
entire organizations to realize that
their practices have to change to be
successful in ad adopting the stch yeah
because I can see that a big change in
attitude in mindset in how we approach
the all release to production what about
things like incremental development
incremental releases is this the
incremental bit still valid with larger
language models or I would say
incrementality and fast releases are
much more important when you have
language models than they are when you
don't in fact I would actually say that
if you are incapable
of creating a release that can go live
to all users on a daily basis now you
may not necessarily do this but you need
to be capable of doing that if you're
incapable of doing that then maybe
language models are not the thing that
you should adopt right now and the
reason why I say that is because you
will literally get from dayto day
different patterns in user behavior and
shifts in that user behavior and you
need to be able to react to that and you
can end up being frankly in a more
proactive workflow eventually where you
can proactively observe okay these were
the past 24 hours of user interactions
we're going to now look for any patterns
that are different from the patterns
that we observed in the past and we find
one and we say okay cool that's a bug
file it away and keep repeating that and
then basically you get into a workflow
where you analyze what's going on you
figure out what your bugs are for that
day you then go and solve one of them or
maybe it was one from the other day who
cares and then you deploy that change
and now you're not only checking to see
what the new patterns are you are
monitoring for two things you're
monitoring for number one did I actually
solve the pattern and behavior that I
wanted to solve for and two did my
change accidentally regress something
that was already working and that's I
think is something that is kind of an
existential problem that Engineers need
to be able to figure out and that's
where observability tools like service
level objectives really really come in
handy because if you have a way to
describe what success means
systematically and through data for this
particular feature you can then capture
all of the signals that correlate with
non-success with failing to meet that
objective and then you can actually use
that to monitor for regressions on
things that were already working in the
past and so creating that flywheel of
looking at data isolating use cases
fixing a use case going in through the
next day ensuring that a you fix that
use case but B you did not break
something that was already working
that's something that's really important
because especially in the worlds of
language models and engineering because
there's a lot of variability there's a
lot of users doing weird things there's
other parts of the system that are
changing the model itself is
non-deterministic it's actually very
easy to regress something that was
previously working without you
necessarily knowing it up front and so
when you get that motion of releasing
every day and and being very incremental
in your changes and proactively
monitoring things and knowing what's
going on that's how you make progress
where you can walk that balance between
making something more reliable but not
sort of hurting the creativity and the
outputs that users expect from the
system okay and observability and you
know and collecting and analyzing data
seems to play quite a crucial role to be
able to do that to do these incremental
steps especially with larger language
models also how use observability to
feed this datab back also for you know
product development maybe product
Improvement new features or something so
can you feed that data back also for
that purpose so far we have talk about
you know replacing the fact that we
cannot really test the system or finding
out if this performing well in terms of
expectations but what about product
development so maybe new ideas new need
to set users find ways of actually doing
stuff with large language models that
you didn't even think of so how can we
use this information to improve the
product so there's really two ways that
I've experienced that you can do this
with our own large language model
features
honeycomb so the first is that yes what
you release first is not going to solve
everything that your users want and so
yes you iterate and you iterate you
iterate you iterate until you sort of
reach I guess a steady state if you will
where the thing that you've built has
some characteristics and it's probably
going to be pretty good at a lot of
things but there will likely be some
fundamental limitations that you
encounter along the way where somebody's
asking a question that is simply unable
with the system that you've built now in
the case of honeycomb I'll ground this
in something real with our natural
language quering feature what people
typically ask for is sort of like a
starting point where they'll say oh well
you know show me the latency for this
service you know what were these like
slow requests or you know what were the
statements that led to slow database
calls and they often take it from there
will they'll manually manipulate the
query because the AI feature sort of got
them to that initial scaffolding we do
also allow you to modify with natural
language so they will often modify and
say oh now groupy this thing or also
show me this or oh I'd like to see a P95
of durations or something like that but
sometimes people will ask a question
where they'll say oh well why is it slow
or what are the user IDs that most
correlate with the slowness or something
like that
and the thing that we built is just
fundamentally incapable of answering
that question in fact that question is
very difficult to answer because first
of all you're not going to be guaranteed
an answer why and second of all we do
actually as a part of our UI have a way
there's this feature called Bubble Up
that will
automatically scan all of the dimensions
in your data and then pluck out you know
oh well we're holding this thing
constant let's say it's Error is
constant what are all the dimensions in
your data and all the the values of
those Dimensions that correlate the most
with that and generate little histograms
that sort of show you that okay yes user
ID correlates with error a whole lot but
it's actually these like four user IDs
that are the ones that correlate the
most and that's your signal that you
should go debug a little bit further
that's the sort of answer that a lot of
people are asking for some signal as to
why and what that actually implies from
an AI system is not just generate a
query they may actually already have a
query but to sort of identify ah based
on this somebody is looking to hold this
dimension in the data constant and what
they actually want to do is they want to
get this thing into Bubble Up mode and
they want it to execute that Bubble Up
query against this dimension in the data
and show those results in a useful way
and that is actually just a
fundamentally different problem than
create a query based off of somebody's
inputs even though it's the same text
box that people are in yeah yeah this
seems to be more about guessing the goal
of the user so it's not about the mean
the rest is the means to an end here you
are talking about understanding the end
they have and then work on that you know
give them the answer they're looking for
right that's true and so the two
approaches that people generally fall
under is they try to create an AI
feature that's like chat gbt but for you
know their their system that can
understand intent and knows how to
figure out which part of the product to
sort of activate based off of intent all
of those initiatives have failed so far
largely because it's so hard to build
and people don't have the expertise for
that so to me looks like that particular
feature requires a certain amount of
context that can be slightly different
from even person to person so not
everybody different users are looking
for something similar yeah but the
similarity means also that there is some
difference anyway and so creating a
system that is able to do that probably
is less obvious than what it seems yes
it absolutely is and so you know back to
this whole notion of incrementality
right
you do want to deliver some value like
you don't want to solve every possible
use case all up front but eventually
you're going to run into these use cases
that you're not solving for and if
there's enough of them like through
observability you can capture those
signals you can see like what are the
things that associate the most with
somebody answering that kind of question
that's fundamentally unanswerable and
that gives you more information to feed
into product development now the other
way that this thing manifests as well is
there's this period of time when you
release a new AI feature where it's like
fancy and new and expectations are like
this weird mix of super high and also
super low kind of depending on who the
user is and you end up surprising your
users in both
directions but eventually it becomes The
New Normal right in the case of
honeycomb we've had this natural
language quering feature since May of
2023 and it's just what users start out
with quering their data with now that's
just how they do it and because of that
there's some limitations right like
there are other parts of the product
where you can actually enter in and get
a query into your data and this quering
feature is not really integrated there
and some people like for example our
homepage does not have the text box you
have to go into our querying UI to
actually get that even though the
homepage does show some queries that you
can interact with we've had users Say
Hey I want this here but we don't
actually really know what the right
design for that is like the homepage was
not really built with anything like that
in mind ever
and yet there actually is a need there
and so this influences it because I mean
this in a way this isn't really any
different from other product development
right you release a new feature it's new
eventually it sort of creates your
product now has a slightly different
characteristic about it you've created a
need because it's not sufficient in some
ways for some users and they want it to
show up somewhere else and that creates
sort of a puzzle of how you figure out
how that feature is going to fit into
these other places of your product is
the exact same principle with the AI
stuff I would just say the main thing
that's a littleit different is that
instead of having very very direct and
often exact needs that people have that
needs that people have or questions that
people want answered are going to have a
lot more variability in them and so that
can sometimes increase the difficulty of
how you choose to integrate it more more
deeply through other parts of your
product okay and talking more a bit more
about prompt engineering so so we said
is at the moment probably is more of an
art than a science right now is because
of the models but how can people use
observability to actually improve their
prompts so because observability it
involves capturing all of these signals
that feed into an input to that system
one of those inputs is the entire prompt
that you send right so for example in a
lot of systems I would say probably most
systems at this point that are being
built people dynamically generate a
prompt or they programmatically generate
it so what that means is okay for a
given user they may be part of an
organization in your application that
organization may have certain data
within it or like a schema for something
or certain settings or things like that
all of those influence how a prompt gets
generated because you want to have a
prompt that is appropriate for the
context in which a user is acting and
you know one user versus another user
they may have different contexts within
your product and so you programmatically
generate that thing so a there's steps
that are involved in programmatic
generation that actually is prompt
engineering even though like it's not
the literal like text itself like
literally just like selecting which
sentence gets Incorporated in the final
product that we send off that is an act
of prompt engineering and so you need to
understand which one was picked for this
user then the second thing though is
when you have the final prompt your
input to a model is literally just one
string it's a giant string well not
necessarily giant but it's a big string
that contains the full set of
instructions maybe there's data that
you've parameterized within maybe
there's a bunch of like special things
you might have examples as a part of
this prompt and you may have
parameterized those examples because you
may have a way to programmatically
generate them based off of somebody's
context and so that right there is
really important because how that got
generated is what's going to influence
the end behavior that you get and your
act of prompt engineering is generating
that thing a little bit better but also
when you have that full text you now
have a way to replay that specific
request in your own environment and so
even though the system that you're
working with is non-deterministic you
might actually get the same result or a
similar enough result to the point where
you can say okay I'm maybe not
necessarily reproducing this bug but I
am reproducing bad behavior with this
thing consistently and so how do I make
this thing more consistently produce
good behavior well you have the string
itself so you can literally just edit
pieces of that right there in your
environment as you're developing it and
you try this thing okay let's see what
the output is I'm going to edit this one
and so on and you get very systematic
about that and you understand what those
changes are that you're doing if you're
good enough which is most people in my
experience you will likely get it to
improve in some way and so then you need
to say okay which parts of this prompt
did we change did we change the parts
that are static okay we should version
this thing and we should load that into
our system now did we improve the parts
that are d dnamic okay what did we
change and why did we change it does
that mean that we need to change how we
select pieces of this prompt
programmatically that's sort of what
observability allows you to do because
you capture all of that information you
can now ground whatever your hypotheses
are in just sort of like the reality of
how things are actually getting built
okay and now I'd like to talk a bit
about how to get started with it you
know for developers that are maybe
starting to work with a large language
models and they want to maybe implement
observability or improve the
observability they have in the systems
they they are creating so my first
question is what are the tools available
to developers to implement observability
for these large language models so it
kind of depends on where you're coming
from so frankly a lot of organizations
already have pretty decent
instrumentation usually in the form of
like structured logs or something like
that and so honestly a very good first
step is to create a structured log of
this is the input that I fed the model
this was the user's input this was the
prompt here's any additional information
that I think is really important like is
metadata that goes into that request
then here's the output here's what the
model did here's the full response to
the model including any other metadata
that's associated with that response
because the way that you call it will
sort of influence that so like there's
parameters that you pass in and it'll
tell you sort of like what those
parameters meant and things like that
just those two log points those two
structured logs this is not the most
perfect observability but this will get
you a long way there because now you
actually have real world inputs and
outputs that you can base your decisions
on now eventually you are likely to get
to the point where there are Upstream
decisions that influence how you build
the prompt and thus how the model
behaves and there may be some Downstream
decisions that you do to act on the data
right like kind of that thing that I
mentioned before where it may be mostly
correct it might be a correctable out
outut and so you may want to manually
correct that thing through code somehow
and so now instead of just two log
points that you can sort of look at you
now have these set of decisions that are
all correlated with effectively a
request and that request to the model
and then its output and some stuff you
do on the back end and some people call
multiple language models through a
composition framework of some kind and
so you may want that full composition
represented as you know sort of like a
tracing through that stuff and by golly
there's this thing called open Telemetry
that allows you to create tracing
instrumentation and gather metrics and
gather those logs as well and it's an
open standard that's supported by almost
every single observability tool so you
may not necessarily need to start with
open Telemetry I think especially if you
have good logging you can use what you
have to a point and incrementally get
there but if you do have the time or if
you simply don't have anything that
you're starting with at all use open
Telemetry and critically you do two
things you install the automatic
instrument
and so what that will do is it will
track incoming requests and outgoing
responses throughout your entire system
so you'll be able to see okay not just
the language model requests that we made
but the actual full life cycle of a
request from like when a user interacted
with thing everything that it talked to
up until the point you know via HTTP or
grpc or something like that until it got
to a response for the end user to look
at that is very very helpful but then
what you need to do is you need to go
into your code and you use the open
Telemetry API which is for the most part
pretty simple to work with and you
create what are called spans a span is
in tracing form it's actually just a
structured log that contains a duration
and causality by default so basically
you can have like a hierarchy of okay
this function call this function which
calls this function and they're all
meaningfully important as this chain of
functionality so you can have a span in
Function One Span in function two span
and function three and functions two and
three are like children of number one so
it sort of like nests it approp
so you can see that nested structure of
how things are going and then you
capture all the important metadata with
like this is the decision that we made
if we're selecting between this Bank of
sentences that we're going to
incorporate into a prompt this is the
one that was selected and like maybe
these are the input parameters that are
going into that function that are
related to that selection it's basically
an active structured logging except
you're doing it in the context of traces
and so that gets you really really
really rich detailed information and
what I would say you can go to open
Telemetry just the website right now and
install it most organizations are able
to get something up and running within
about 15 minutes and you know then it
becomes a little bit more work with the
manual instrumentation because there's
an API to learn so maybe it takes a
whole day but then you need to sort of
make some decisions about what the right
information to capture is and so that
may also take another day or so
depending on how much decision fatigue
you end up with and you know if you're
if you're trying to overthink it or
something like that one thing also that
I wanted to ask about the information to
track that I think we haven't mentioned
so far because you mentioned inputs
outputs but then also reading your book
you put a high emphasis on errors as
well so tracking them in this case with
open Telemetry say so with your
observability tool so why are errors so
important why do we need to track them
so errors are critically important
because in most Enterprise use cases for
large language models the goal that they
have is they want to Output a Json
object I mean it could be XML or yaml or
whatever but like we'll call it Json for
the sake of Simplicity it's usually some
Act of a combination of smart search and
useful data extraction and putting
things together in a way such that it
can fit into another part of your system
and hopefully like the idea is that that
thing that you've extracted and put into
a particular structure accomplishes the
goal that the user had in mind that's I
would say is like 90 plus percent of
Enterprise use cases right now and will
likely always be that so there are ways
that things can fail so first of all
your program could crash before it ever
calls the language model well yeah you
should probably fix that the system
could be down open AI has been down in
the past people have incidents well if
it cannot produce an output period okay
you should probably know about that
it could be slow and you could get a
timeout and so even though the system
wasn't down well it's effectively down
as far as your users are concerned again
you should know about that and the
reason why you should know these kinds
of failures right now is because some
are actionable and some are not
actionable so if say you get a timeout
or the system is down you get a 500
maybe there's a retry or maybe there's a
second language model that you call as a
backup maybe that model is not as good
as the first one that you're calling but
it might be more reliable or something
like that there's all these little
puzzles that you can play there and so
you need to understand which one is
which and you need to track that in
observability so you can understand if
there's any patterns that lead to some
of those errors but then you get to the
most interesting one which is what I
call the correctable errors which is
that the system is working it is
outputting Json but maybe it didn't
actually output a full Json object right
maybe for the sake of latency you are
limiting the output amount to be a
certain amount but the model needed to
Output more than like what your limit
actually was and so it just stopped well
that is an interesting problem to go and
solve because maybe the answer is to
increase the limit a little bit or maybe
it's that you actually have a bug in
your prompt where you are causing the
model somehow through some means to
produce way more output than it should
actually be outputting and so you need
to systematically understand when that
happens you then need to also
systematically understand when okay it
did produce an object but it needed to
have like this name of a column in a
schema somewhere or something like that
but it gave a name that was like not
actually the same name or maybe this
object structure had like this nested
object inside of it that needs to have a
particular substructure and maybe it's
missing one piece of that substructure
for some reason and like you could
imagine if you look at the output oh
well if a human were tasked with
creating this Json like maybe they would
have missed that thing and so you need
to track when those errors actually
happen because that could be it's valid
Json so it parses but it's not actually
valid as far as your system is concerned
so what are those validity rules what
are the things that it fails on how can
you act on that is that something that
you can improve your prompt engineering
or if when you're actually validating it
and like you actually know what the
structure should be you have enough
information to like fill in that Gap can
you actually just fill in that Gap and
what we observed with honeycomb in our
quer pre assistant feature is that we
had none of these like correctable
outputs on the beginning or rather we
did not try to correct those outputs in
any way at first and so what we noticed
is about 65 to 70% of the time it was
correct but then the rest of the time it
would error it would say can't produce a
query and when we looked at those it had
valid Json objects coming out but they
were just like slightly wrong and we
then realized in that parsing thing oh
crap we actually can't like if we just
remove this thing this may not be
perfect but it's actually valid and
maybe that's good enough for the user or
we know that it's missing X but we know
what x is so we're just going to insert
X because we know that like that needs
to be there for this to work and boom
it's good to go and we were able to
improve the overall like end user
reliability of the thing from like a 65
to 70% of the time to like a 90% of the
time like this is a massive massive
Improvement that we were able to do just
by fixing these things now the remaining
now it's like six s% of reliab
that was through like really hardcore
prompt engineering work that we had to
do that took a lot more time but so I
think why that's really important is
like we were able to fix that like 20%
plus Improvement within about two weeks
and so you can have that degree of
improvement within about two weeks if
you systematically track your errors and
you differentiate between which one is
which and so this kind of a long-winded
answer but I think it's really really
important because the way that you act
on errors matters so much in this world
now I think at the end of of our time so
I've got maybe some final questions so
the first one is about the current
limits of what we can do with
observability for large language models
are there any things that at the moment
are not really possible but we wish they
were I will say one thing that I really
wish that I had that I did not have is a
way to meaningfully apply other machine
learning practices on this data so not
like AI Ops or you know something like
that
but pattern recognition so these classes
of inputs lead to these classes of
outputs that's effectively like that's a
collection of use cases if you will that
are like thematically similar and we had
to manually parse all of that stuff out
and like humans are good at pattern
recognition but it would have been so
nice if if our tool could actually
recognize that kind of stuff the second
thing is that observability and getting
good instrumentation to the point where
you have good observability it's an
iterative process it's not something you
can just slap on one day and then you're
good to go it takes time takes effort
and you don't get it right often you
need to constantly improve it and kind
of that's frankly hard and I wish it was
a lot easier and I'm not really sure I
know how to make it a lot easier but
like what that means is you may think
that you're observing these user
behaviors but you're not actually
observing everything that you need to be
observing to improve something and so
you will be doing a little bit of guess
work and then you have to go back and
figure out what to reinstrumentation
a tool and API and SDK standpoint I just
wish it were a lot easier to sort of get
like a oneandone approach or like maybe
I do iterate but I iterate like on a
monthly basis instead of on a daily
basis until I feel like I have good good
data well maybe any of these of what you
said these current limitations being
addressed in the next say few years or
also there are other things that you see
happening in terms of observability
engineering for llms you know things
that you think will improve new things
that we cannot do now is that any work
in progress yes I would say there
definitely is on the instrumentation
front right now it's not just language
models but there's like vector databases
and Frameworks that people use and
there's sort of like a collection of
tools and Frameworks that are relevant
in this space none of those right now
have automatic instrumentation in the
same way that like HTTP servers or
message cues have automatic
instrumentation today so the act of
getting that auto instrumentation via
open Telemetry is like you kind of have
to do it yourself that's going to
improve over time I think but that's a
real need because that sort of first
pass at getting good data is harder to
come to today than it should be the
second is that your analysis workflows
in tools are a little bit different some
tools like for example honeycomb are
actually very well suited to this and so
what I mean by that is when you're
dealing with textual inputs and textual
outputs these values are not
meaningfully pre aggregable meaning that
you can't like sort of just turn it into
a metric like you can other data points
and they tend to be high cardinality
values so like there's likely a lot of
unique inputs and a lot of unique
outputs and a lot of observability
systems today really struggle with high
cardinality data because it's not a fit
for their backend and so if you're using
one of those tools then this might be a
lot harder to actually analyze and it
might also be more expensive to analyze
than you would hope it is
and so I hope that like I mean high
cardinality is a problem to solve like
independent of llms it's something that
you need period because otherwise you
just don't have the best context what's
going on in your system but I think llms
really forces the issue on this one and
so I hope that this causes most
observability tools to handle this shape
of data a lot better than they do
today okay thank you now we came to the
end I think we've done quite a good job
of introducing observability for large
language models but is there any
that you would like to mention anything
else that maybe we forgot I would say
that getting started with language
models is super fun and it's super weird
and it's super interesting and you're
going to have to throw a lot of things
that you know out of the window and
that's what makes them so exciting and I
think that like you should look at how
your users are doing stuff and some
things that they struggle with and just
pick one of those and see if you can
figure out a way to Wrangle a language
model to Output like something useful
like it doesn't have to be perfect but
just kind of something I think you'll be
surprised at how effective you can be at
doing that and turn something from like
a creative wish to like actually a real
proof of concept that you might be able
to productionize and so I wish there
were a lot more better practices around
how to do this stuff but that will
likely come I think a lot especially in
2024 there will be a lot of demand for
that and so I think you should get
started right now and like spend an
afternoon seeing what you can do and if
you can't get it done like I don't know
reach out to me and like maybe I'd be
able to help you
out okay thank you Philip for coming to
the show has been a real pleasure this
is joavan asoni for software engineering
radio thank you for
listening thanks for listening to SC
radio an educational program brought to
you by It software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at SE-R doet
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack Channel at
seo. slack.com you can also email us at
team
e-r. this in all other episodes of SC
radio is licensed under creative
comments license
2.5 thanks for
[Music]